A Guide to the Arlington County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1786-1899
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Arlington County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1786-1899
The Library of Virginia
Arlington County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1786-001-1899-010
Digital images
Arlington County (Va.) Circuit Court
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Digital images were generated by Backstage Library Works through the Library of Virginia's Circuit Court Records Preservation Program.
Historical Information
Chancery Causes are cases of equity. According to Black's Law Dictionary they are "administered according to fairness as contrasted with the strictly formulated rules of common law." A judge, not a jury, determines the outcome of the case.
Arlington County was originally named Alexandria County. It was formed from a portion of Fairfax County that Virginia in 1789 ceded to the federal government for use as the site of a new national capital. In 1801 the area officially became part of the District of Columbia, although Congress named it Alexandria County. By an act of 9 July 1846, Congress returned the county to Virginia, and the General Assembly extended the commonwealth's jurisdiction over the region effective 20 March 1847. By an act of assembly passed 16 March 1920, the county's name was changed to Arlington, the name of the Custis family mansion (the home of Robert E. Lee), which is located in the county.
Scope and Content
Arlington County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1786-1899, are indexed into the Chancery Records Index. Cases are identified by style of suit consisting of plaintiff and defendant names. Surnames of others involved in a suit, including secondary plaintiffs and defendants, witnesses, deponents and affiants, and family members with surnames different from the plaintiff or defendant are indexed. Chancery causes often involved the following: divisions of estates or land, disputes over wills, divorces, debt, and business disputes. Predominant documents found in chancery causes include bills (plaintiff's complaint), answers (defendant's response), decrees (court's decision), depositions, affidavits, correspondence, lists of heirs, deeds, wills, slave records, business records or vital statistics, among other items. Plats, if present, are noted, as are wills from localities with an incomplete record of wills or localities other than the one being indexed.
Chancery cases are useful when researching local history, genealogical information, and land or estate divisions. They are a valuable source of local, state, social, and legal history and serve as a primary source for understanding a locality's history.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
See the Chancery Records Index found on the Library of Virginia web site for the chancery records of other Virginia localities including city of Alexandria.
Additional post-1899 Arlington County Chancery Causes are available in their original format at the Library of Virginia.
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Arlington County (Va.) Circuit Court.
Subjects:
African Americans--History.; Business enterprises--Virginia--Arlington County.; Debt--Virginia--Arlington County.; Divorce suits--Virginia--Arlington County.; Estates (Law)--Virginia--Arlington County.; Equity--Virginia--Arlington County.; Land subdivision--Virginia--Arlington County.
Geographical Names:
Arlington County (Va.)--History.; Arlington County (Va.)--Genealogy.
Genre and Form Terms:
Chancery causes--Virginia--Arlington County.; Deeds--Virginia--Arlington County.; Judicial records--Virginia--Arlington County.; Land records--Virginia--Arlington County.; Local government records--Virginia--Arlington County.; Plats--Virginia--Arlington County.; Wills--Virginia--Arlington County.
Selected Suits of Interest
- 1805-039: Bazel, an enslaved person vs. James Kennedy, Jr., etc.:
  Freedom suit.
- 1819-045: Ambrose Vasse vs. James English:
  Debt suit involving the sale of a slave, William. Seller (Vasse) is afraid that buyer (English) will sell slave to a slave trader before fully repaying his debt. Vasse is also concerned that sale to trader will force William to leave his wife and child.
- 1822-018: John Mason vs. John Muncaster and others:
  Cause involves a dispute related to the purchase by Mason of glebe land in Fairfax Parish from the Protestant Episcopal Church of Alexandria, or as it became known in 1814, Christ Church. The source of contention between the plaintiff and the defendants was the question of whether Christ Church of Alexandria had jurisdiction within Fairfax Parish and therefore had the authority to sell the land. The plaintiff in his bill and amended bill and the defendants in their answer provided very detailed legal and historical arguments to support their claims. The defendants in their answer presented a history of how Christ Church acquired land in Fairfax Parish from the parish's inception in 1765. In the process of doing so, they discussed the nature of the relationship between the two churches in the parish, Falls Church and Christ Church; how the parish was governed; and the decline in membership of Falls Church. Plaintiff and defendants provided evidence to support their arguments such as a copy of a bill from a previous chancery case involving Christ Church, a copy of a Supreme Court mandate, a copy of a deed, and correspondence. The chancery cause also includes miscellaneous papers related to the case such as subpoenas, affidavits, and depositions.
- 1827-036: Administrator of William Stewart, Jr. vs. Catherine Flood McCall and others,:
  Stewart was the manager of nail factory in Alexandria owned by Catherine Flood McCall. The cause inludes correspondence between Stewart and McCall. The major themes found in Stewart's letters to McCall include: his affectionate feelings for McCall and desire to marry her; business matters related to McCall's nail factories in Alexandria and Richmond and her plantation in Tappahannock; his difficulties with McCall's enslaved property who worked for him at the factory; his constant lack of money to pay his personal debts; his efforts to make additional income outside the factory (one effort led to his being sued by the United States government for violating the Embargo Act of 1807); his repeated requests to be given total authority over McCall's financial interests; his poor health, both emotional and physical; and his great unhappiness with his life in Alexandria.
- 1845-017: Bank of Potomac, etc. vs. Edward Sheehy and wife, etc.:
  Ship manifest listing names of slaves to be transported from Alexandria to New Orleans. Includes depositions from a few slave traders acquainted with the slave markets of the Deep South. eponents were examined in order to obtain knowledge regarding the fluctuating prices of enslaved people in various markets and their depositions provide information on the fluid nature of slave market value in relation to the rise of fall of other commodities such as sugar and cotton.
- 1848-006: Admr. of Robert Marshall vs. Exr. of Richard Marshall Scott, etc.:
  Cause involves importation of enslaved people from Fairfax County to Charles County, Maryland. It also includes portion of Richard Marshall Scott' memoir sharing family history to his son and correspondence between Scott and his son.
- 1849-001: William Taylor, etc. vs. Admr. of Thomas Vowell:
  Two African-Americans claimed to be illegally detained as enslaved people. Defendant forcibly removed the two from Washington, D.C. and put them a slave jail in Alexandria owned by James Bruin. The defendants threatened to sell African-Americans before their petitions for freedom could be heard in D.C. Circuit Court.
- 1850-008: Benoni Wheat, etc. vs. Phineas Janney, trst(s), etc.:
  Dispute between rival members of Methodist Episcopal Church in Alexandria for control of church property. One group supported Methodist Episcopal Church, South and the other remained loyal to Methodist Episcopal Church, North. Dispute centered over slavery. Court decided in favor of Methodist Episcopal Church, North.
- 1850-012: John E. Hughes, etc. vs. Joseph Bruin, etc.:
  Bruin was leading slave trader in Alexandria, Virginia. One of his agents purchased an enslaved girl named Mary Catherine from a Frederick Vaccari. The agent and Bruin were told she was enslaved for life. After a brief stay in Bruin's slave jail, they sent her to Georgia along with other slaves to be sold. Plaintiffs claimed the enslaved girl should not have been sold out of the state because she was not enslaved for life. Mary Catharine was to be freed when she reached the age of 25. One of the previous owners of Mary Catharine named her after his two daughters, Mary and Catharine. The suit offers insight into domestic slave trade.
- 1851-011: Catherine Jones vs. George Kephart, etc.:
  Freedom suit. Catherine Jones claimed to have been emancipated and unlawfully sold.
- 1852-024: Moses, an enslaved person, etc. vs. Exrs. of William H. Foote:
  Freedom suit. Moses and other enslaved persons of William H. Foote claimed to have been emancipated by Foote. They successfully won their freedom.
- 1856-022: Robert W. Carter, etc. vs. Exrs. Of John Tayloe, etc.:
  Estate division suit that originated in Richmond County. John Tayloe was one of the wealthiest Virginians at time of death in 1828. Owned vast amount of real and personal property including Botetourt County. Includes will listing names and locations of multiple plantations. Built Mount Airy in Richmond County. Includes correspondence that discusses political environment in nation in 1852.
- 1859-017: Exr. of George Washington Parke Custis vs. Mary Ann Randolph Lee, etc.:
  Custis was stepgrandson of George Washington. Robert E. Lee was his executor. Mary was daugter of Custis and wife of Lee. Additional defendants were Lee's children. R.E. Lee sought the court's help in settling Custis' vast estate in order to repay Custis' debt which was between 11,000 and 12,000 dollars. He had a question regarding whether or not he could sell slaves (200) to repay debt even though Custis' will stipulated all his slaves were to be emancipated 5 years after repaying debt. Lee writes about difficulties managing slaves who believed they were to be immediately emancipated. Cause includes inventory of Custis' slaves. Custis' will listed as exhibit but not found in suit.
- 1860-003: Mary Ann Junius vs. Henry W.P. Junius:
  Scandalous divorce suit. Defendant was a bigamist and con artist. His exploits are detailed in suit. Ranged from Virginia, South Carolina, Kentucky, Indiana, and New York.
- 1865-017: Moses Hepburn vs. Prudence Crandell Hepburn, etc.:
  Moses Hepburn was a free African American. He was the son of William Hepburn, a white Quaker merchant who owned substantial property in Alexandria County, and an enslaved person named Esther. Cause contains William Hepburn's will in which he leaves most of his estate to his children by Esther. Cause centers on sale of property along Alexandria Canal and division of proceeds among Heburn's children by Esther. Moses Hepburn's claims to property disputed by Willaim Hepburn's legitimate children.
- 1866-011: Henry Grafton Dulany vs. Richard H. Dulany, etc.:
  Henry Grafton sued Richard H. for failing to abide by will of Henry G.'s father Henry Rozier Dulany in order to inherit Henry R.'s estate Shuter's Hill. Will stipulated that in order for Henry R.'s daughter Rebecca Anne to inherit estate whoever she married had to change his name to Henry Rozier Dulany and build a monument to Henry R. on estate. Otherwise, Rebecca's brother Henry G. would inherit Shuter's Hill. Rebecca married her cousin Richard H. He refused to change his name and failed to build monument. Henry G. sued and won.
- 1866-013: Robert F. Roche vs. Fannie Roche:
  Divorce suit. Fannie refused to go with husband to his house on wedding day. Robert accused her of being a prostitute. She leaves for New York City. Cause includes tintype of Fannie used by processor to identify her.
- 1866-017: Phillipine Durand vs. Claudius Durand:
  Divorce suit. Couple from France who moved to U.S. in 1835. He left her. She started a new life making a living by sewing. She made enough money to purchase land in Fairfax County. He returned and demanded she give him her property. Court sided in her favor.
- 1867-006: George W. Parker vs. Mary Jane Parker:
  Divorce suit. Married as enslaved people in Petersburg, VA in 1855 or 1856. White person performed marriage but was not licensed to do so. Wife left husband before passage of cohabitation act in 1866. Cause dismissed because couple were never legally married.
- 1868-030: Sarah E. M. Field vs. George W. Field:
  Divorce suit. Husband abandoned wife to join Mount Vernon Confederate regiment in May 1861. He supported secession. She supported union. Cause includes letter written by wife to husband. She shares her hatred for secession "and all its hateful helpers."
- 1870-004: Nancy Hodges vs. John H. Broders:
  Contract dispute. Nancy Hodges was a free African American. Her husband was a slave named Tom Hodges owned by Broders. Nancy made an agreement with Broders to purchase her husband's freedom. She accused Broders of not abiding by agreement. He threatened to sell her husband to slave speculators.
- 1888-004: S. Ferguson Beach vs. Alexander Hunter, etc. and Alice A. Hunter, etc. vs. S. Ferguson Beach, etc.:
  Cause contains a pamphlet for the sale of Abingdon Plantation, a property previously owned by the Custis family and the birthplace of Nelly Parke Custis Lewis.
- 1895-011: James Underwood vs. Thomas S. Clark, etc.:
  Debt for the training of racehorses Clara Bell, Gladstone, and Brooklyn. Mentions racetracks at St. Asaph and Alexander's Island.
- 1897-006: Sarah G. Johnson vs. Louis H. Crowe, etc.:
  Sarah G. Johnson sues her former husband, Louis H. Crowe, for not paying for land she deeded over to him while they were married. Johnson asserts she was the legal owner of the land before the marriage and that after she deeded the land to Crowe, he physically drove her off the property. However, Crowe claimed that he was driven from the land and was forced to jump from a second story window, breaking his leg, to save himself from her violence. See also 1891-002-Sarah G. Crowe vs. Louis H. Crowe.